# Thomas McMaster BSc (Hons)

C.V.

# **Data Development and Application Support.**

#### **Contact Information:**

Email: <u>tommcmaster@protonmail.com</u>

LinkedIn: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/thomasmcmastersql/">https://www.linkedin.com/in/thomasmcmastersql/</a>

Portfolio: <a href="https://thomas-mcmaster.github.io/">https://thomas-mcmaster.github.io/</a>

#### **Personal Statement:**

I am an IT professional who specializes in relational database development, administration and ETL. My main skills are in SQL Server (2008 R2 to 2019) and automation using Microsoft PowerShell. Since 2004, I have built up a wealth of experience in roles in the public, private and charitable sectors. In each of those roles, I have produced high quality work against deadlines that has helped organisations and colleagues improve their IT processes.

#### **Personal Attributes:**

- Punctual, dependable and highly reliable.
- Efficient, highly organized and able to meet deadlines.
- Able to work effectively as part of a team or as an individual with my own sense of motivation.
- Excellent face-to-face and written customer support skills.

# **Professional Qualifications:**

• Microsoft Certified in Azure Fundamentals (AZ-900).

# **Professional Experience:**

#### March 2022 - present

**Data Engineer - Hymans Robertson** 

Technologies: SQL Server 2008 R2 to 2019, PowerShell, SSIS, SSRS, Azure Dev Ops, Data Factory, Synapse Analytics, Kimball Data Warehousing Concepts, Yaml, Bicep

- Analysis and delivery of changes to SQL-based data for pension scheme administration.
- Introducing Cloud technologies via 'proof-of-concept' projects for Azure Data Factory / Synapse Analytics.
- Online resources managed via CI and CD YAML-based pipelines and Bicep.
- Engineering with Powershell to automate the transfer and anonymisation of data between environments.
- Delivery of solutions and collaboration with colleagues via Git and Azure Dev Ops (ADO).
- Involvement in important finance industry projects including the UK government's Pensions Dashboard and making pension scheme data securely available online.

# September 2020 -March 2022

Senior Data and Integration Officer - East Renfrewshire Council.

Technologies: SQL Server 2008 R2 to 2019, Oracle 12 to 19c, Powershell, SSIS, SSRS, Git, RMAN.

- Council DBA with responsibility for the Authority's SQL Server and Oracle database estate.
- Automation of data transfers with scripted WinSCP.
- Delivery of new reporting suite to monitor health of the Council's database estate.
- Delivery of Git source control for DBA team projects and code.
- Working with suppliers and third parties to ensure smooth on-premise and on-premise-to-cloud migrations.
- Introduction of nightly Oracle 'hot' backup solution to increase service availability.
- Creation of SQL Server corruption checker. Nightly check of 450 SQL databases for new DR strategy.
- Maintenance of Civica Icon and Servitor, NEC's Revenue's and Benefits, NEC Ohms and Tribal's K2.
- Ongoing review of database security, roles and the planned release of encryption-at-rest for SQL Server.

# February 2019 - September 2020

Database Developer and BI Analyst – Maggie's Centres.

Technologies: SQL Server (2008 R2 to 2017), thankQ CRM, SSIS, SSRS, VBA, Microsoft Office

- Automation of IT processes (financial pipelines, stewardship communications, ETL and event promotion).
- Monitoring and resolving database performance issues, backup strategy and scheduled maintenance.
- · Requirements analysis with support staff, colleagues at 26 NHS hospitals and senior stakeholders.
- · Processing of requests sent to the Database Service Team's inbox.

# **June 2011 – February 2019**

Systems Analyst / Programmer / Team DBA – Hymans Robertson

Technologies: SQL Server 2008 R2 to 2016, T-SQL, SSIS, MS Access, VBA, SSRS, Civica UPM2 and W2.

- Working in the Third Party Administration Practice as part of the Technical Development Team.
- KPI and SLA reporting to Management.
- Application support for the UPM2 pension management system and its underlying SQL Server databases.
- Trouble-shooting and root cause analysis of Helpdesk System Support requests submitted by end users.
- Communication with stakeholders to identify issues, gather requirements and produce specifications.
- Lead analyst on Practice projects for high profile clients.
- Business process and work flow analysis.
- Team DBA role to maintain and update UPM2 and its associated SQL Server instances.
- Guiding junior analysts and developers.

#### June 2010 - June 2011

**Database Programmer – Hewlett Packard** 

Technologies: SQL Server 2008 R2, SSRS, VBA, Microsoft Office

- Working with EMEA Software team to develop relational database systems for use in sales reporting.
- Development, set up and enhancement of relational databases using T-SQL, SSIS and Microsoft Access.
- Analysis and development of existing business processes for conversion to relational databases.

## March 2007 - June 2010

Asset and Systems Support Officer – East Ayrshire Council Roads and Transportation Service Technologies: SQL Server 2000 to 2008 R2, Microsoft Office with VBA, Classic ASP.

- Service contact for all IT requests, trouble-shooting and application support.
- Analysis and development of bespoke database applications for use by Roads Service staff.
- Administrator of GGP Gazetteer software.
- Maintenance of the authority's street gazetteer and associated data to BS7666 standard.
- Secretary of the Scottish Gazetteer Group.

#### June 2005 - March 2007

I.T. Technician - Booth Welsh Automation Ltd

Technologies: Microsoft Office with VBA.

- Responsible for IT system and application support across three sites.
- Working with end users across the business to assist with hardware and application issues.
- Development of relational database applications for all departments in the company.
- Support and enhancement of Pegasus accounting software.

#### June 2004 – June 2005

Systems Analyst (Contracting) – GlaxoSmithKline

Technologies: Microsoft Office with VBA, AspenTech process engineering tools.

• Development of Microsoft Excel and VBA tools to interact with the process engineering software.

# **Education:**

# 1999-2003:

• Honours Degree (2:1) in Computer Studies from Glasgow Caledonian University.